soft engineering radio episode 117 brand
silicon um
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
support
[Music]
good thank to you wherever you are my
name's Lawrence Kratz we're here a
beautiful day in Cambridge my guest
today is Brant Selleck we're talking
today about UML - Bram was the chair of
the UML - task force involved in
formalizing and defining UML he's been
working with it since around 1996
he's currently present of Malina
software before that he was a
distinguished engineer at IBM and before
that a founder of object times it's a
gentleman with a very long history in
the modeling world and a great deal of
experience with it so I'll now hand over
to Brian to introduce ok hello Laurie
it's a pleasure to be here I'm here at a
conference that I'm enjoying very much
on cogeneration I guess the reason
you're talking to me has to do with my
UML experience and my model driven
development experience which goes back
about 20 years before it was called
model driven development the main
subject today is model stuff in general
so for those of our listeners who aren't
familiar with this please give a quick
introduction to modeling in general just
as a high-level overview
ok.well modeling is something that I
guess engineers have been doing forever
in fact if you go back to the oldest
known engineering textbook written by a
guy called Vitruvius written in the
first century BC you'll see actually he
dedicates almost an entire chapter to
modeling but modeling is essentially a
technique that's used to help people
understand complexity and deal with
complexity so it's been around in
software forever I mean it certainly
things like flowcharts are essentially
models and if you like the essential
property of models is the fact that they
raise the level of abstraction and by
eliminating detail which is not relevant
for whatever you're interested in so
software and modeling have go back a
long way although there's quite a nasty
history of modeling in in software and
some very negative experiences that I
guess I would trace back to the fact
that most modeling in the past was based
on very
vaguely defined modeling concepts and
therefore the problems that resulted
were problems that ended up with the
model not being accurate at all or being
very open to interpretation and as
Bertrand Mayer said once very nicely
bubbles and arrows don't crash it was a
which probably captures the essential
attitude that a lot of software people
have towards models that you know
they're just documentation however
there's been a move afoot for a while
now maybe even starting as far back as
the fourth so-called fourth generation
languages to use modeling as possibly
something more formal and we're now
entering a phase where we have more
formality in in in modeling and and in
fact to the point where some people are
using modeling languages as
implementation languages but there's
certainly a range of the way that people
use models they use them for
documentation they use them for
communication very informal
communication as a way of capturing
ideas and as I said at the extreme end
if you like they're also using it as an
implementation facility in much the same
way that people used say languages like
Fortran to raise the level of
abstraction above the language like
assembly and machine code so this is
what one often hears the term sketching
and blueprints and and you have
effectively outlined those two I think
the latter one being the blueprint it's
there sufficient detail there to
actually end up with some large part
maybe a complete part of a running
system at some point that's true
although you know sometimes these ways
of using models and software are
perceived as being mutually exclusive I
don't think they are and maybe that's
one of the interesting differences say
between these high-level modeling
languages and programming like
high-level programming languages the
fact is that programming languages are
pretty unforgiving once you get to a
programming language you have no choice
but to be precise modeling languages
should give you a little more latitude
in fact the ideal modeling language
would give you some kind of setting
where you would go from say informal
completely informal and
in many ways unstructured unconstrained
to something which is fully formal and
it should be a progression hmm but
certainly these two ways or if you like
styles of using models are not mutually
exclusive you would want to be able to
use high-level modeling concepts just
sketch out ideas without being hindered
by some automated system telling you you
know you've forgot the period to the
point where you say okay now I'm
actually I actually want that yep okay
so I mean we obviously cannot talk about
modeling without talking about UML which
is the de-facto modeling language now so
could you give us a quick introduction
for those who are not most people we can
assume a reasonably familiar with UML
but just giving us an idea of you what
stage a UML is at today where is it
being used
okay well UML it's got an interesting
history and maybe it's worth repeating a
bit because that will it'll be
understood better and perhaps tolerated
a little more I guess in their own they
started the nine these late 80s there
was an outburst of interest in
object-oriented systems
object-oriented systems because they're
not so much algorithmically based but
more have a very strong structural
component lend themselves very nicely to
different kinds of abstract
representations that often are
describing topologies things like
inheritance hierarchies relationships
between objects or classes of objects
and so on so what happened at that time
late 80s early 90s was that there was a
profusion of notations modeling
notations that basically allowed people
to represent object relationships and in
in some typically graphical form
so the idea of modeling languages
started emerging as a first class idea
if you like and unfortunately about that
time there were I think 90 or so
published modeling locations and methods
and people are getting pretty upset with
that because you would find tool vendors
that supported some of these things but
unfortunately they were the only tool
vendors were so you either chose a
particular notation you were stuck with
a vendor and most of those vendors were
not particularly stable they'd go
bankrupt get bought up at what or
whatever and the result was that this
was a very unsatisfactory situation not
to mention the fact that of course there
were so many people with so many
different ideas or ways of representing
the same idea which was even worse so
the idea that came around in the 90s I
think the person who basically drove it
was was the president of rational
Software Mike Devlin who basically had
one of the so-called three founders of
UML Grady Booch working for him and at
that time another very popular method
was the OMT method started by Jim
Rumbaugh and the first version of UML
was basically a synthesis of the work of
these two gentlemen
and so Jim rambha and Grady Booch
and they were later joined by Ivar
Jacobson who worked more on the front
end stuff having to do with use cases
and so on so the very first version of
UML was known as 0.9 which was primarily
intended as a documentation support
that's a kind of a power assist it
wasn't really envisage as being
something that could even be used as an
implementation tool so that gives you
some understanding of the underpinnings
of UML in other words the the the
although there was significant work done
to
than its semantic base that was more of
a of an afterthought so to speak and I
would credit Steve cook with
contributing a lot to that with the
introduction of the object constraint
language which was a language that he
had helped develop at IBM and that gave
some more formality to the definition of
UML but that was what eventually came
out as an OMG standard in the OMG is the
object management group which at that
time was trying to consolidate and
define a set of standards for
distributed systems and object based
stuff the systems and naturally they
turned to notations and modeling
languages so when they put out a request
for proposal for a modeling notation to
support this kind of application
rational contributed to it and then
invited a number of other researchers
and industry experts to contribute to it
so the end result was UML 1 which is
probably the result of the work of maybe
a dozen people at least and it was an
interesting combination of very good
ideas proven in various places but of
course not all good ideas work together
very well though there's there were a
number of issues and of course there was
some commercial pressure and things like
that although a lot less than people
imagine you know there's there's this
perception that somehow standards are
driven by the big companies to a certain
extent there is some of that but I would
say not a dominant thing in fact I would
say that standards are probably mostly
driven by strong personalities and and
you know you can take that any way you
like but you know some somebody with a
particularly adamant view might get
their stuff through even though it
doesn't necessarily fit in with
something else and so on so after a
while there had been up to that point a
number of companies a number of
enterprises that were actually trying to
push modeling beyond this documentation
paradigm
move it forward towards what we now call
model driven development possibly even
with bull cogeneration and so on so I
guess maybe around in the late 90s or
possibly even later I can't remember the
dates anymore
what happened was this party so to speak
of people who wanted to take UML further
took over and the proposal was put out
for a new version a revised version of
UML that would support this model driven
development idea further so they've been
a number of versions of UML 1.1 1.2 and
so on and those were just incremental
updates to the first version of UML but
there was a push for a very different
and that's that's right so what happened
was essentially as you say most of the
revisions of UML 1 or actually the very
first version was called UML 1.1 most of
them were just incremental improvements
fixes and so on although one interesting
idea that came in a relatively late in
that first version of UML and I would
credit Philippe de Frey with with that
was this notion of profiles yep and UML
was always defined as a language that
could be customized but the notion of
actually a profile which is some kind of
consolidated refinement of UML or a
particular domain or purpose didn't
crystallize until the profile in concept
was introduced I think in 1.3 or 1.4 and
then later on I guess 1.5 is also
somewhat significant milestone and it's
actually a bridge between UML 1 and UML
2 we introduced what was known as the
action semantics which is kind of a UML
virtual machine and that of course
required a lot more formality and a lot
more precise definition of semantics and
so on that was originally defined as a
separate an addendum to UML it was
integrated into your mell 1.5
and that was actually pretty much
preserved in UML to that aspect of it
but when you Emil too came around there
was a not many new feature there were
not many new features added I would say
the four prominent features all had to
do with in terms of modeling
capabilities all had to do with the
ability to scale things up so that
modeling which of course makes most
sense when you have complex systems
could handle complex systems more
effectively the first of these had to do
with the ability to model structure
complex structures so basically an
architectural description language was
fitted in so to speak into the
structural modeling capabilities of UML
based on a very recursive approach where
you defined a system as consisting of a
number of parts each of which of course
could all itself be decomposing and a
number of parts that are connected by
explicit connections that represented
communication link and so on and that
was or modeling of course very complex
architectures how do we compare that to
class diagrams because I think most of
our listeners will be familiar with
class diagrams so the representing
programs is sort of a moderate level of
abstraction so can you compare the
actually that's a really good question
and it's it's one of the problems that
we've had with UML two is that people
because they're so familiar with class
diagrams tend to confuse the structural
modeling which is primarily captured in
the concept of collaborations which is
by the way of course a highly misleading
name because collaborations in UML are
actually have primarily a structural
concept but there's history behind that
that probably isn't all that interesting
but the contrast is is quite significant
and the problems that we're finding is
that people are still expecting to see
class diagrams and interpret these
structure diagrams as class diagrams the
difference is that class diagrams
basically define relationships between
sets
so we can talk about the relationship a
between the set of customers and the the
set of banks or we can talk about the
relationship between set of insurance
policies and insurance policy users or
whatever but these are set relationships
and there are certain things that are
actually abstracted away so for example
if you and I have a particular
relationship and we belong to different
sets that specific relationship will get
lost in the class diagram
structure diagrams on the other hand are
capable of showing relationship between
individual members for example imagine a
relationship between save three nodes
that are connected in a ring in a ring
configuration in other words my left
side is connected to your right side and
we go around until we come full circle
that kind of relationship is actually
very difficult to model with class
diagrams but is quite explicit as a ring
in a structure diagram or a
collaboration diagram so the difference
is quite significant but strangely
enough at least for me because I've been
working on instance based modeling for a
long time most people find that
confusing yet you know what I find is
that if you ask a layman a person off
the street to show you something to do
to say to draw a diagram of their family
they're not gonna draw a class diagram
they're gonna draw a structure diagram
or a collaboration diagram saying well
here's my mom here's my dad and here's
me and my sister and here's Uncle Sam
and so on and that as I say is not
something you can capture properly with
collaboration with I'm sorry with
plastic Rams but with collaboration
diagram
so that's a--that's a significant
difference so that's one addition that
we put into UML - in terms of its
modeling capabilities another one that I
would single out is quite significant is
the addition of complex end to end event
behavior description communication
events and this is the notion of
interactions and there was a form of
this so called sequence diagrams in UML
one unfortunately it did not scale up so
we use pretty much the same principles
that we used in the structure modeling
in other words applying the same set of
concepts hierarchically so that you
could have an interaction diagram that
basically invokes another interaction
diagram and you could get a lot of
scalability out of that and also the
ability to model certain interesting
situations that occur in these
interaction diagrams that such as the
ability to represent choice such as the
ability to represent interleaving and
the ability to represent things like
assertions behaviors that must happen
and differentiate them from behaviors
that may happen so there's quite a rich
language in here that was again to
attribute this I think the person who
had most influence on this was øystein
Hogan who had worked on this same
problem in inside the ITU with
International Telecommunications Union
and they had defined a standard way of
modeling interactions and sequence
diagram so most of this work was ported
over into UML because it was a proven
thing and standards should work with
proven things
the third kind of new feature that was
added in there was a rework of the
feature or sorry the process modeling
capabilities of UML or behavioral
modeling specifically so-called activity
diagrams and activity diagrams existed
in UML one but through some misguided
choice which looked good at the time we
basically put them on top of state
machines there's some formal similarity
or semantic similarity between state
machines and activity diagrams so the
basis for activity diagrams in UML one
were state machines which meant that
there was a coupling between the state
machine formalism and the activity
modeling formalism we found that this
coupling was unfortunate because it
limited the way the expressive power of
activity diagrams one of them being that
activity diagrams had to be well
structured in the Dex Trask sense or the
sense of block structured programming
languages and yet you wanted to model
things like business processes or signal
processing flows which were not
necessarily always well structured so
this was reworked this whole part of UML
was reworked and again given a recursive
definition so that you could define
activities that can potentially composed
of other activities and so on and this
is going by I'm picking up a big theme
here about the scalability so a lot of
the improvements are not just the
extensional I mean you split those two
languages into but at the same time try
to make it so you can use them bigger
and bigger examples precisely and you
know as I said basically you need this
because you need modeling most where you
have a complex system so the ability
scale UML up to large systems was
perhaps one of the themes of UML too
the last thing I would say that we added
in there was the same kind of concept
into state machines which already had a
lot of that in there but now we were
able to modularize the state machine so
that a state was something it could be
actually reused for example between
multiple state machines and a state
being something could actually hide an
entire
this other state machine inside it that
gave us again that scalability property
that we talked about before and the
modularity property so those are the new
features the only other thing I would
sort of highlight us as of being a
feature of UML too is the more solid
semantic foundations and and I have to
explain that here because there's a lot
of people who claim that UML has no
semantics it's just a bunch of notation
well that's patently untrue just so just
for clarification because I mean the
word semantics does in itself confuse a
lot of people so what we're meaning here
is very simply what UML means in the
sense of when I draw uml model or
represent a UML model this is what it
means so that I have the same
understanding that you do when I give it
to you that's correct and it also means
if you like if we want to make that a
little more precise it means first of
all what does UML intend it to model UML
is intended to model running software or
specifications of software both of these
things so when we talk about the
semantics of UML basically it's exactly
as you say what does it mean what kind
of for example behavior is this
representing or what kind of
specification or organization of the
specification is it is it is it
identifying or describing so semantics
is very important and of course if we
want to do things such as generate
programs directly from UML models the
semantics cannot be ambiguous but they
have to be precise enough so that a
compiler or some kind of translation
system can translate this unambiguously
into a program now UML itself is
intentionally have has certain vague
parts to it which are called semantic
variation points unfortunately not all
of them have been explicitly identified
it's one of the failings of UML two but
we tried very hard to at least identify
the key ones and the idea behind these
semantic variation points goes very
nicely with the idea of
files which is that you can tighten the
semantics of UML to suit it to your
purpose for example things like the
scheduling policy a UML has nothing to
say about whether what kind of
scheduling policy you have whether it's
first-come first-serve priority-based or
anything like that there's basically a
placeholder in UML where you can place
your own scheduling policy so that's
just an example there's I think
somewhere in the order of 90 such
semantic variation points that have been
explicitly identified in UML and now
this this is presumably comparable to
something like say see if you take the C
standard there are specifically it's
saying at this point you're integer size
depending on the platform your choice we
give you some overall constraints within
which that choice has to happen but the
specific details are down to you that's
really yeah yeah that's what that is
Oh unfortunately or fortunately depends
on your point of view there's still a
lot of vagueness in the in the UML spec
and part of that has to do with the
history probably if we did it now we'd
do it quite differently and and maybe
the time has come for people to start
thinking about that I have been asked
what is the future is there going to be
a UML three well and we'll certainly get
on to that question I've been interested
to ask you that when they talk I would
like to go back just to the definition
of UML two because that's clearly one of
the main things is to sort of tighten it
up and scalability we you alluded
earlier to OSI all the object and
straight language so would you like just
tell our listeners what that is because
I think a lot of people will have seen
it a little bit maybe not quite sure
where it's used and certainly what
impact it could have and pursues and
horrified by it in some sense or at
least put off by it simply because it
has a syntax which some people find
unusual but it basically as I said I
think ocl is a wonderful invention I
think anybody who understands high
school
math probably can master it in a couple
of hours the object constraint language
I said was introduced by Steve cook it's
actually a subset of the language that
he had helped define at IBM primarily I
think for business type applications so
it was used to define constraints
constraints a thing that specifically
constraints on class diagrams so you
might have a constraint that says there
might be some exclusion between
different kinds of different subclasses
of a particular class or think you know
you might want to be able to say if I'm
using this subclass I cannot use that
other subclass
because it's basically first-order
predicate logic which sounds
intimidating but it's something that
most programmers understand and Steve
cook to his credit tried to make it a
little more familiar by eliminating what
is normally the symbology of math such
as the upside down a and the backward E
and saying for all or exists and things
like that which read a little bit better
and and then programmers might find
familiar but for those who are
intimidated by ocl I would certainly
encourage them to have a look at it and
you'd be surprised how easy it is to use
and to learn of course so these
constraints are effectively extra things
on top of my class diagram being a
sequence of types I mean gain if I go
back to programming languages something
I'd like to often say is this variable a
is all integers greater than 0 for
example I can't all I've got those as an
integer type and if I've got a
constraint I can express that extra
thing that extra bit of information so
that presumably is what's allowing me to
more tightly define the semantics
because I can start narrowing things
down and further and further in greater
detail exactly and and well sail can
actually be used to has been used in two
different ways one is of course it was
used to define UML itself to make the
semantics of UML more precise but also
it is a part of the language in a sense
although it's a right now a separate
specification that comes out of the OMG
but they work together and you as a user
have the choice of using ocl as a
straight language to further constrain
your model and be more precise with it
you could use other languages as well
then perhaps ones that you're more
familiar or even math if that's what you
like but certainly ocl was intended to
work and is semantically aligned with
UML
so um one other thing that anyone who
looks at the definition of UML too will
see is that everything is split up into
lots of little packages which are
somehow merged together could you just
give us a brief idea of overview of
package much do you mean package merge
or the overall view of the metamodel and
actually probably but both because this
is reconnecting so I do warn people not
in to be careful to treat oh there be
dragons if you get into the UML
metamodel part of it because it turns
out to be a complex thing part of it
because there's probably better ways of
doing it that we weren't quite sure how
to do it right
and this by the way I would I would cull
out as a general statement about
modeling languages we don't know how to
do these things
there is no theory of modeling language
design that we can resort to and
identify what's good what's bad and and
what should be done which way and so on
so there was a lot of discovery that
took place when we built the UML meta
model but it's partitioned in a number
of ways having to do primarily with
domains of concern or we feel like
modeling areas so for example state
machines are packaged separately from
activity diagrams which are packaged
separately from things having to do with
structure modeling and so on in fact one
of the other things that was done in UML
2 was a much clearer definition of the
compliance levels of UML although I to
be to be frank here no vendor that I
know cares much about this but they
should and certainly I think users
should press vendors to to conform to
these so there's 16 a maximum of 16
compliance points which sounds like a
lot except that UML 1 had
to to the 43rd power or something like
that possible
I think these women's having zeros that
has so the idea that we had then was of
course to modularize the language and
and one of the ideas behind that was so
that people even though yes you are
mental to is a big language it is
possible to only use a subset of it and
that subset can be very very small the
smallest subset of your mental list is
intentionally chosen to model something
like Java it's it's quite crude and
doesn't have any behavior or things like
that but it will allow you to model Java
like C++ C sharp like things so one of
the interesting things that we found we
discovered a number of interesting
mechanisms that would help us build this
meta model in other words a definition
of UML and one of the things that we did
there was something called package merge
which turns out to be a very very tricky
operation subsequent to the definition
of UML to I I initiated some research
into this concept of package merge and
we found all kinds of issues and
difficulties with the way it was defined
but nonetheless it's there and the idea
of package merge is to allow you to
incremental e define concepts and that
incremental 'ti was useful when you
wanted to have compliance points so you
might have start off with say a very
primitive notion of class that like I
said maybe it's all good enough to model
Java like classes but when you get into
more sophisticated things such as the
ability to model classes that have an
internal structure to them like a
something like a collaboration structure
that goes far beyond what Java can
support and therefore the idea was to
allow some kind of mixin of additional
capabilities to the concept so that's
how package merge works but again it's
quite a challenging the idea the basic
idea is a simple one it can be made to
work has been made to work but it's
to be a trickier thing than most people
thought okay okay and this is presumably
all part of trying to make the
definition easier and do you think you
know future versions it the UML - could
be the definition could be made simpler
then or that the language might become
smaller again or well definitely it it
can be consolidated and you know if you
can avoid the second system syndrome
which to a certain extent we did
replaced from the feature side on the
other hand from the definition side we
we we went wild so yes definitely there
could be a consolidation and there is
this appeal now that says let's try and
define a solid theory of modeling
language design based on what we've
learned from defining languages like UML
various dia cells and so on and let's
see if based on that we can possibly do
it better I won't say right but let's
say we can do it better the next time
around okay so moving on to slice
related but slightly different topic and
one of the things that people are
obviously care a great deal about is
tool support of the various standards
and I mean a lot of our listeners will
be familiar 'the now i'll once upon a
time with rational rows for example so
could you give us an idea of the tool
support for UML - or a lot of the tools
maybe that they're still more UML one or
sort of UML 1/2 1/2 - or well I don't
know that many vendors that are
supporting you and mill one anymore
when we define UML - by the way we did
try to make it backward compatible or I
can't remember whether it's fully
forward compatible but anyway it was the
idea was that you should be able to in
the vast majority of cases take your UML
1 model and just move it into UML - with
little or no adjustment so as far as I
know from all the tool vendors that I
know practically everybody is into UML -
now and and that's because I think UML
ACTU actually has received a fair amount
of publicity
and people want to hear about UML too
would are not interested in buying UML
one tools but you want to buy the latest
and greatest so most of them do support
UML two and it's interesting there is
some consolidation one of the things
that happened was there was an
open-source project to release the UML
to metamodel as defined by the OMG on
top of eclipse and that has actually
been used by a number of tool vendors as
their that the the core of their UML 2
tool so he's saying that that tools are
then built in a clip so that they 'then
that's right yeah the tools can be or
basically have a common metamodel inside
so that also gives them the ability that
to upgrade the model as soon as the
metamodel um giametta model has changed
and that happens every now and then in
fact this week I guess on June 27th will
have UML 2.2 but so these vendors can
easily move up to the next version
simply by incorporating the new meta
model which generally tends to be upward
compatible so you mentioned the open
source tolling there and under Clips
maybe you could talk a little bit more
about Eclipse and if you're aware of any
other open source tools because often
that's something that gets people hooked
into right stuff well there's at least
three open source versions of UML that I
know of I'm a little hesitant to mention
them just so that in case I am it one or
two so to be fair I won't talk about
them but if you go to eclipse.org I
suspect you can find a good list of
eclipse-based UML tools these tools are
well some of them are free not all of
them which is kind of interesting it
creates an interesting situation because
people it has created a mindset that
tools should be free and having worked
for tool builders for the last 20 years
I can tell you this is a problem because
when people find out they have to pay
thousands of dollars for a tool that
they figure they can get for free
it sounds paradoxical but without trying
to be or commercial or anything like
that I can tell you that there is a
difference in terms of the scalability
and the ability to integrate with other
tools that you still won't find in
open-source tools that you will find in
commercial tools and and therefore it's
not a bad idea to start off with say an
open source maybe an eclipse-based tool
but but I would imagine that people will
find these limiting very quickly if they
start using modeling as a full-fledged
part of their development process rather
than just as a power-assist
so that's that's quite an important
things well you don't normally think
about well can the tool do a compare
between two models and how good and
effective is that can the tool deal with
the fact that in the model might be
partitioned and into five different
segments you will does it require that
all everything be loaded into memory or
does can it work with parts of it and
with just partial models that kind of
stuff is something a commercial vendors
have to worry about that the open source
tools typically and freeware tools don't
don't deal with that well let's say I
mean if you had to summarize the
relative support of UML two amongst
tools and sort of a nutshell what would
it be well it's I would say it's by far
the dominant in fact the dominant
modeling language that's supported by
modeling tools
except ok so moving on the game does
something slightly different a lot of
people will have heard of the the Magic
three letters moth MOF and they've heard
of it
Germany in conjunction with UML could
you just give us a very brief overview
of that relationship whether that's
changed at all in UML - well moth stands
for meta object facility and basically
it's a tool it's a domain-specific
language modeling language that's used
to define modeling languages now the
thing that makes it particularly
confusing is that in in in essence it is
really a subset of UML because to define
a modeling language you have to
basically define what is the set of
concepts that your language supports and
what are the relationships between them
it turns out that class modelling and
things around related to that is
practically all that you need so there's
actually a great deal of commonality
between moth and UML which is captured
in this thing called the UML
infrastructure now the UML
infrastructure is therefore a shared
library between the moth which adds a
few additional concepts on top of that
and and UML which adds a lot of concepts
on top of that but the interesting thing
is it's in a sense semantics free
because it's supposed to support a
number of different things like UML and
like the moth and the moth really deals
with static structures therefore for
example moth has no behavior in it or
very little definitions of behavior
whereas UML of course is opposed to
model dynamic software so things like
state machines activity graphs and
things like that are all part of of UML
so in a sense it's a semantics free
library that repeats that consists of a
number of structural patterns and end
rules for defining them so the moth is
still used in fact to define modeling
languages it is it was used to define
UML it's being used to define other
modeling languages at the OMG is
standardizing
and it's uh in my opinion pretty good
although again there are complaints that
it's too complex so it's been broken
down into two parts a core part called a
moth or essential moth which is
essentially derived from the Eclipse
modeling tool called EMF there's the
similarity in names isn't accidental and
which is like I said basically if you go
back to what I said earlier good enough
to model the structural relationships of
object-oriented programs like Java so
that's a very basic subset and and a lot
of modeling is now being done and meta
modeling or metal modeling language
definition is being done with EMF rather
than with the foam off okay so know
basically well if you what you're saying
it's more feces for defining new
modeling languages what modeling
languages have a normal common right in
your end user is unlike do come across
them off directly it's just those who
want to dig that level deeper that's
right yeah it is you know it sort of
don't try this at home kind of thing
because like you say most of these
language definitions tend to be very
technical and it's easy to confuse
things especially if you're a UML users
because of the similarity between them
off and the UML and people get very
easily confused because the moth is
about UML and UML is about an
application and sometimes it's difficult
to or it's easy to confuse these two
when you get into this world so the
so-called meta world which which
definitely is confusing for those who
are interested in learning about this
and all the intricacies there's an
excellent book called get LS your BA by
Doug Hofstadter it was written in the
80s and it's all about self definition
and reflection and recursion and this is
all present unfortunately in in in the
modeling language definition and so be
careful with it it's try this at home I
like that advice um and so you mentioned
the one of the current hot topics and I
feel we're always prone to this with the
main specific languages could you to
give us an idea about the relationship
to DSA
and also that you may want to bring in
about profiles which he mentioned
earlier okay so well the idea of
domain-specific language is yet another
old one we had lots and lots of
domain-specific programming languages in
the past you worked in a number of
companies wherever the company had their
own programming language particularly
suited for their purpose because it gave
him the expressive power that they
needed that wasn't provided by the
general-purpose language and so on it's
interesting just to reflect a little bit
on the history of that you don't see
many of these domain-specific
programming languages around a lot of
that has to do with the tooling not with
the idea still people actually do need
the the ability to be very precise to to
capture the main specific subtleties in
a succinct way therefore there's always
a need to specialize something that
comes as a general-purpose facility so
if UML is a general-purpose language it
was intended to cover a very vast range
of application domains
although remind everyone to say to
remember that you the UN UML doesn't
mean universal it was not meant as a
universal language but as a unified
language to unify these different ways
that people had of basically specifying
the same thing so
there is now a I guess a view in a lot
of people's minds that you either use
UML or you use a domain-specific
language say if you're working on
telephony or you're working on insurance
you'd like to have a language that has
telephony concepts or insurance concepts
in it so that brings you much closer to
the problem domain and then gets you
away from worrying about how do I cast
this a general concept to make it look
like the concept that I want it to be so
that's that's some necessary thing and
undoubtedly we will need domain-specific
languages but it's not a question of
either/or because of the profile
capability of UML which gives you the
ability to actually refine UML
to produce a domain-specific language
and there's a number of examples of that
many in fact and and again to quote
Steve cook he said almost everybody who
uses UML either implicitly or explicitly
used and uses it with a profile the
profile mechanism was one of the things
we did add to UML two we didn't improve
on as much as we could including for
example the ability to when you define a
profile remove those parts of UML which
you're not interested in and therefore
you can reduce UML to a subset which is
very domain-specific so the advantages
of doing that are quite significant it
turns out because it's a general-purpose
language UML usually has the base
concepts that you want concepts like
object concepts like class all of these
things it turns out most domain-specific
modeling languages are going to have
this so either you're gonna roll your
own and then possibly repeat some
mistakes that that are common because
again we don't have that theory of
modeling language design or you can
reuse some of the work that went into
things like UML other advantages are the
fact that people know about UML and and
therefore you probably don't have to
work as hard to teach them the the your
variant of UML your domain specific
variant of you a milk but perhaps most
important is the fact that a proper
profile a well-defined UML profile is
something that can be used with any UML
tool and therefore the infrastructure
that's needed to support a language a
domain-specific language isn't as
expensive to build if you do a profile
then it is compared to a language that
you defined from scratch and unless
people think that this isn't such a big
deal I do remind you that around the
language particularly if you want to use
it for things like cogeneration you have
to have a vast array of very complex
tools you have to have tools that do
different merged they can tell versions
you have tools that actually can
version your models you have to have
tools that that compile your model you
have to have tools that do things like
linking they have tools that do analysis
of your models so just having the
ability to say create an editor for a
domain-specific language is far from
sufficient so profiles do provide you
with that capability and to a certain
extent if you have a number of
domain-specific languages that are all
based on UML there's a much better
chance that you can integrate the models
that you produce assuming that these
models aren't represent different facets
of a single system it's it's so easier
because there's a common semantic
underpinning behind behind these
profile-based dsls to integrate and come
up with a unified or integrated
definition of your complex system so
these are some of the advantages
unfortunately we need to be honest the
profile mechanism is something that grew
out of a simple idea and again just like
with the package merge there are
subtleties to it that haven't been
properly explored and you can certainly
shoot yourself in the foot or or hang
yourself with the rope or whatever the
right word is here or with if you don't
do this right and there isn't very much
guidance on how to do it right so people
also probably be aware of a couple of
languages for example sysml which they
may well have heard of relation to you I
mean are these domain-specific languages
would you say what's their relationship
to UML well sis amel specifically is a
profile of UML and there's a number of
profiles that are now being quite have
received quite a lot of attention one of
them is the UML profile for dota mo DAF
which is dota and Mota for standards
issued by the US Department of Defense
and the Ministry of Defense in in the UK
that's mod F which is basically a way of
specifying both requirements and system
architectures so that these contractors
large systems contractors that support
military systems
can farm out there so they're their
requirements system requirements so
these languages were defined
independently omental and then it turned
out that a profile could could could
actually be used to represent these
languages and the reason people are
doing this
including sysml is because of the
ability reuse tools that's I would say
the primary motivation behind that so
you don't have to have although what
you'll find is the tool vendors
themselves have to build in not just the
ability to support a profile but to
customize the tool so that the concepts
that are in the in the profile can also
appear as first-order concepts and say
the graphical representation sysml is an
interesting profile from one specially
interesting profile from one perspective
in that it's gone beyond the modeling of
software UML as I said was intended to
design software and a little bit of the
environment around that software things
like actors and so on but in a very
crude way sysml actually goes much
further and it goes beyond just the
ability to model software it gives you
the ability to model Hardware of
different kinds or even what is awfully
called wetware in other words humans
animals other things that that a system
a complex system of systems might
involve so
sysml is now receiving a lot of
attention from the systems engineering
community which has always been dealing
with complex systems and now it gives a
path because it has its in semantically
integrated with UML it gives people some
kind of continuum so that they can start
off with a system model and then farm
off parts that I can now be modeled in
UML without introducing a major
discontinuity in the process okay so I
think one another thing that we have to
relate UML to is is MDA model-driven
architecture slash model driven
development slash model driven
engineering whichever three-letter mm
term people use to describe it so
there's a lot of interest and
controversy around MDA now one of the
big terms that one here is there is this
whole converting a platform independent
model to platform specific model I've
heard you talk about platform
independence versus platform ignorance
and that's running if you could fill our
users in on that and then relate things
back to UML okay well let me start off
with the term model driven yeah you
picked a sore point here I actually
think that's a terrible term my acronyms
have a B in them not because of brand
but because I prefer to call these
things model based I'm worried a bit
about the I guess buzzword backhand
backlash hey it can happen
MDA is sin MBD are things that are
buzzwords right now and of course
eventually there will be some
disappointment because there's always
over promise in these things and people
will say it might actually end up with
the same fate as case which is a
forbidden term now but as in case tools
okay so exactly computer-aided software
engineering because it was over-promised
there although you know people said case
tools failed I don't think they failed
they basically went on and became model
driven tools by evolving to a certain
extent or the next generation of these
things so that case was a necessary step
but the problem with model driven
is it gives you the impression that
somehow the models are driving this but
it really isn't the case as I said
modeling has been used in engineering
including software engineering forever
so it's really a bad term that can
actually trip some people up because
they're there they might actually think
that they have to somehow drive their
designs by models rather than models are
something that you need to produce along
the way but you're really driving its
application driven design always and
models have a role to play in this a
significant one but they're certainly
not the focus
you know the objective is not to produce
models but but so that's why I think
model-based is a better term for this
but the idea behind model based software
engineering and now I guess extending to
model-based systems engineering is that
models now play a role that's quite
significant they pass play a central
role as opposed to a second-order role
and therefore including things such as
the ability to generate code for models
now there's one of very amazing property
- - software based models that you won't
find in any other engineering discipline
that's that's quite fortuitous that
allows us to do a lot more with models
in software than in any other
engineering discipline that's the fact
that for one the model and the system
that are is being modeled share the same
medium and that medium is a particularly
interesting medium because it's a medium
that's very well suited to automation so
you can in a sense go from a model to an
implementation
without the standard discontinuity that
you have between models and
implementations is standard engineering
where suddenly you're confronted you
know you may have a beautiful
computer-aided model of your car but now
you have to cast it into metal which you
have to bend and then there's this huge
discontinuity in the process you have to
use different tools different people
different skills different processes
whereas with model driven development or
model-based development you have to
basically you can just go through a
progression maybe use the same tools all
along the way the same skills the same
people so that's quite significant
now the model-driven architecture is
actually a copyrighted term it is
different than model driven development
or model based development whichever you
prefer
model-driven architecture is was
copyrighted by the OMG not because they
want to protect the copyright but they
just want to make people aware of a
formal definition behind it it's not a
standard although people that keep
thinking of it as a standard or
referring to it as a standard it's not a
standard what it is it's an initiative
or to define a set of standards that
support model-based software engineering
or model-based systems engineering and
therefore then while it involves things
like UML it involves things like mauve
it involves things like sysml so these
are all standards that are part of that
MDA initiative the idea of MDA and
model-based development has got a number
of interpretations depending on what
what your starting point is I would say
there's two key elements to model-based
systems engineering software engineering
that are essential that I would put
before talking about platform
independent and platform specific models
idea number one is to raise the level of
abstraction so that we're not mucking
around at the level of programming
languages which are unfortunately still
too closely related to implementation
concerns you really have to understand
computers quite well in order to be able
to use a programming language
much more so than when you're using a
modeling language which hopefully gets
you much closer to your problem domain
so raising the level of abstraction is
undeniably a good thing and that's a
core property of model-based engineering
um the N and we did that in the past
when we went from assembly to high-level
what so called
third generation or high-level languages
and and the productivity difference was
enormous the other aspect is also
something we did at the same time which
was to support to support this process
with automation in other words use
computer-based automation to help us
bridge the gap between the high level
specifications that are based on this
more abstract representation into
programming implementations or
computer-based implementations and so
those are I'd say automation and
abstraction are the two fundamental
properties of model-based engineering
and these are undeniably good you can
argue about whether UML is the right
thing or the wrong thing and so on but
you do want to you cannot argue against
these two ideas so excuse me are you
saying that UML is playing the role of
the third generation programming
language there or is the UML just one of
the possibilities I mean it's one of the
possibilities and the profiles in fact I
expect to see more and more profiles as
says you know some people like to see
this is a continuum where we started off
with machine language and went on to
assembly and went on to third generation
languages fourth generation languages
well there was even a fifth generation
we can argue about that one but the idea
is that there is a progression basically
taking us over higher levels of
abstraction and thing to remember is
what we're trying to abstract out is the
technology that the implementation
technology which brings us to this
platform independent model plat for
space specific model business
that I think is quite confused a lot of
people in fact most people if you talk
to they talk about MDA they immediately
switch to PIM platform-independent model
and prism platform specific model
terminology taking that as the essence
of MDA hmm the one of the problems we
run into so the idea of just explained
it very briefly the idea is that when
you define these things at a very high
level of abstraction you are ignoring or
or abstracting away the implementation
technology you don't care whether it's
running on top of Linux whether it's
gonna be in C or C++ or a job or
whatever that is your your worrying
about your application and that's a very
powerful idea that simplifies your
problem because you're not worrying
there's a whole area of concerns that
you're not dealing with it also gives
you the ability to get portability from
one platform to another so that's the
idea of the platform independent model
it turns out of course when you start
trying to implement this you suddenly
have to bring in elements of the
platform in there and that's where the
idea of a platform specific model comes
in so there's this fundamental
differentiation between the two that
says I'm now progressing towards an
implementation implementation in the end
is a working program and the progression
might be safe from a platform
independent model to a product specific
model to maybe a program an
automatically generated say C or C++
program that represents your your
platform independent model your
application down to actually a running
executable and the the problem though
that I see with platform independent
models and the term is that it's
misunderstood to mean platform ignorant
models and people are very much focused
on intentionally ignoring any factor in
the underlying platform
that as meant as much of it as they can
and and usually they assume it means
100% now it turns out that of course the
physical world has something to say in a
software that interacts with with it and
therefore you of course ignore some of
the aspects of that physical world at
your own risk so for example if you
assume that your software is let's say
you're designing software to deal with
that to communicate with a satellite if
you ignore the fact that it may take
minutes before your message gets from
where you sent it to the satellite your
software is not going to be very good
and it's not gonna work right so physics
has something to say with about all of
that and you know with inter based
internet-based systems that we have
nowadays what you'll find is that
physics plays a more and more prominent
role in more and more applications and
therefore people who are unaware of
these things of thinking that somehow
this can be retrofitted through
something called a platform-specific
model in other words the first time to
consider any effects of the underlying
physics is and when they get to the
platform specific model are probably
going to be in error and are going to be
very surprised that they actually have
to take some of these factors into
account very early in the design and so
is the way that you see this that
someone will be using let's say a UML or
your more profile model and there'll be
some sort of platform-specific
annotations I mean for example if I've
got my spacecraft which you know
obviously a piece of software I write
quite frequently that I can sort of
specify this is a communication going
over interplanetary things or this is a
local one and in some way that I can
differentiate yes there's ways of doing
that but but the point is that you have
to recognize that there is that space in
between that's the first thing and
therefore this is something that you
have to put into your so-called
platform-independent model
in a sense space as part of your
platform so that's why I'm objecting to
the term not so much of the term as to
its interpretation so yes the next thing
to do you might actually have the
ability might have to have
specifications about what your
assumptions are about the physics
underneath and there's ways of
specifying that in a way that is
platform independent in other words you
define it in terms of what kind of
physical properties you expect you're
not talking about any particular
technology necessarily but but you are
talking about what kind of expectations
you might have for example in terms of
communication bandwidth memory size CPU
horsepower if you like these are things
that matter when you design at the
highest level of abstraction quite often
you know I would equate that with what
traditional engineers do when they
architect for example a building or a
bridge they're very much aware of the
limitations of the materials that they
work with and they work with that in
mind and the architecture reflects that
very much okay so moving towards our
finale as it were I stopped you earlier
you were talking to us about the future
of UML so could you give us a few words
on that please you know Mel 3
fortunately well I think now is not the
time to touch UML too much now is the
time to understand how to design things
like UML 3 so in my view we really
should be and I expect that to be the
case simply because the users of UML
could not I think take another version
major revision of UML right now so this
is a good time to consolidate understand
and possibly simplify and and build your
mail based on some deeper understanding
of the foundations behind modeling
languages and that whatever that is it
may not even be UML although UML is
going to be my assumption like Fortran
it's gonna be around forever and there's
gonna be a UML 7 very likely just like
there is a Fortran whatever is 2008 I
don't know if there's one now but I'm
sure there will be so so that's gonna
stay around but in my opinion the future
is
with more modern languages and and the
Khans time of consolidation is now to
understand how to do these things and
develop a sound engineering theory
behind this so that just like I can with
say a programming language that I want
to design I can go and buy a book now
and it's a problem that's been studied
and and systemized or systematized if
you like and now it's reproducible
that's what engineers should be working
with systematic and reproducible methods
and and patterns and then approaches and
I should be able to go and buy a book on
how to design my domain-specific
modeling language and and design it
according to what theory and experience
has shown to work ok well thank you very
much for any selmak thank you my
pleasure
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website and s/ii -
radio dot length if you want to support
us you can donate to the SE radio team
via the website or you can advertise for
su radio for example by clicking on the
dick reddit delicious and slash dot
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team @ SE - radio net or if it
is specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under a
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pod safe music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle
[Music]
you